<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>

    <!-- Pentateuch -->
    <string name="bible_book_genesis_synopsis">Genesis narrates the beginning of everything: the creation of the world by God, the fall of Adam and Eve, Noah's flood, the scattering of peoples after the Tower of Babel, and the story of the patriarchs Abraham, Isaac, Jacob, and Joseph. Its central theme is the origin of humanity and of the nation of Israel, as well as God's promise of redemption.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_exodus_synopsis">Exodus tells how the Israelites were freed from slavery in Egypt under the leadership of Moses, through the ten plagues, the crossing of the Red Sea, and the giving of the Ten Commandments at Mount Sinai. Its focus is the deliverance of the people and the covenant established between God and Israel.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_leviticus_synopsis">Leviticus gathers the laws, rituals, sacrifices, and purity regulations that God establishes for the Israelites, guiding how the people are to live in a holy way and maintain their communion with Him. Its central theme is holiness and right worship.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_numbers_synopsis">Numbers recounts the journey of the Israelites through the wilderness toward the Promised Land and takes its name from the censuses taken of the people. Between God's faithfulness and the people's repeated rebellions and lack of faith, its central theme is trust in God along the way.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_deuteronomy_synopsis">Deuteronomy gathers the final speeches of Moses before Israel enters Canaan, recalling the Law and the events of the wilderness and urging the people to obedience and faithfulness to the covenant. The book ends with the death of Moses and the preparation for a new stage in Israel's history.</string>

    <!-- Historical Books -->
    <string name="bible_book_joshua_synopsis">Joshua recounts the conquest of Canaan under Joshua, the successor of Moses: the crossing of the Jordan River, the fall of Jericho, and the division of the Promised Land among the twelve tribes of Israel. Its central theme is God's faithfulness in keeping His promises and the call to courage and obedience.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_judges_synopsis">Judges shows how, after Joshua's death, Israel falls into cycles of turning away from God, oppression, and deliverance through judges such as Deborah, Gideon, and Samson. Its central theme is the consequences of unfaithfulness and God's mercy in raising up deliverers.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_ruth_synopsis">Ruth tells the story of the Moabite widow who, in the time of the judges, follows her mother-in-law Naomi to Bethlehem and marries Boaz, becoming the great-grandmother of King David. Its central theme is loyalty, kindness, and the providence of God, who redeems through a kinsman-redeemer.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_1_samuel_synopsis">1 Samuel recounts Israel's transition from judges to monarchy: the ministry of Samuel, the rise and fall of King Saul, and the anointing of David, including the account of David and Goliath. Its central theme is that God looks at the heart and exalts the faithful.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_2_samuel_synopsis">2 Samuel narrates the reign of David over Israel, with his victories, his sin with Bathsheba, and the turmoil within his own family. Its central theme is God's covenant with David and the consequences of a leader's choices.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_1_kings_synopsis">1 Kings tells of Solomon's reign, the building of the temple in Jerusalem and, after his death, the division of the kingdom, along with the ministry of the prophet Elijah before King Ahab. Its central theme is that faithfulness to God shapes the fate of kings and people.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_2_kings_synopsis">2 Kings follows the decline of the kingdoms of Israel and Judah, the ministries of Elijah and Elisha, and the falls of Samaria to Assyria and Jerusalem to Babylon. Its central theme is the consequences of persistent unfaithfulness.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_1_chronicles_synopsis">1 Chronicles retells Israel's history through genealogies and the reign of David, with a focus on worship and the preparations for the temple. Its central theme is the people's identity and the centrality of worshiping God.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_2_chronicles_synopsis">2 Chronicles narrates Solomon's building of the temple and the history of the kings of Judah, emphasizing religious reforms and ending with the fall of Jerusalem and the decree to return from exile. Its central theme is faithfulness in worship and the hope of restoration.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_ezra_synopsis">Ezra recounts the return of the exiles from Babylon, the rebuilding of the temple, and the reforms led by Ezra to restore the Law among the people. Its central theme is spiritual restoration grounded in the Word of God.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_nehemiah_synopsis">Nehemiah narrates the rebuilding of the walls of Jerusalem under his leadership, despite opposition, and the renewal of the people's covenant with God. Its central theme is perseverance, prayer, and leadership in the work of restoration.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_esther_synopsis">Esther tells how, in Persia, the Jewish queen Esther risks her own life to save her people from Haman's plot to destroy them, an event that gives rise to the feast of Purim. Its central theme is God's hidden providence and courage at the right moment.</string>

    <!-- Wisdom & Poetry -->
    <string name="bible_book_job_synopsis">Job tells the story of a righteous man who loses everything and, together with his friends, wrestles with the meaning of suffering, until God answers him out of the storm. Its central theme is faith and trust in God amid suffering that cannot be explained.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_psalms_synopsis">Psalms gathers 150 prayers and songs — of praise, lament, thanksgiving, and trust — many attributed to David, expressing the full range of human experience before God. Its central theme is sincere worship in every season of the heart.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_proverbs_synopsis">Proverbs collects short sayings, largely attributed to Solomon, that offer practical wisdom for daily life. Its central theme is that the fear of the Lord is the beginning of wisdom.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_ecclesiastes_synopsis">Ecclesiastes presents the Preacher's reflections on the brevity and apparent futility of life “under the sun.” Its central theme is that true meaning is found in fearing God and enjoying His gifts.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_song_of_songs_synopsis">Song of Songs is a poetic dialogue celebrating the love between a bride and her beloved. Its central theme is the beauty and dignity of love and commitment.</string>

    <!-- Major Prophets -->
    <string name="bible_book_isaiah_synopsis">Isaiah warns Judah of judgment because of sin but proclaims hope, foretelling restoration and the coming of the Messiah, the Servant who suffers for the people. Its central theme is God's holiness, judgment, and redemption.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_jeremiah_synopsis">Jeremiah calls Judah to repentance before the Babylonian exile and announces the promise of a new covenant written on the heart. Its central theme is faithfulness amid judgment and the hope of renewal.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_lamentations_synopsis">Lamentations gathers poems of mourning over the destruction of Jerusalem and the temple. Its central theme is grief that, even in pain, still trusts in God's mercy.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_ezekiel_synopsis">Ezekiel, in exile, receives striking visions — such as the valley of dry bones and the new temple — that announce judgment and restoration. Its central theme is the glory of God and the promise of a new heart.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_daniel_synopsis">Daniel recounts how, during the Babylonian exile, Daniel and his friends remain faithful to God — in the fiery furnace and the lions' den — and receive visions about future kingdoms. Its central theme is God's sovereignty over history and faithfulness under pressure.</string>

    <!-- Minor Prophets -->
    <string name="bible_book_hosea_synopsis">Hosea tells how God commands the prophet to marry Gomer, an unfaithful woman, as a living picture of Israel's unfaithfulness and God's persistent love. Its central theme is God's relentless love and the call to return.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_joel_synopsis">Joel, in the face of a devastating locust plague, calls the people to repentance and announces the outpouring of God's Spirit. Its central theme is the day of the Lord and the call to wholehearted repentance.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_amos_synopsis">Amos, a shepherd called to prophesy, denounces the social injustice and empty religion of Israel. Its central theme is that God demands justice and righteousness, not mere rituals.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_obadiah_synopsis">Obadiah is a brief oracle against Edom for its pride and its violence against Judah. Its central theme is the justice of God in the face of arrogance.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_jonah_synopsis">Jonah tells how the prophet flees God's call to preach in Nineveh, is swallowed by a great fish, and, after preaching, resents God's mercy toward the city. Its central theme is the breadth of God's compassion.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_micah_synopsis">Micah denounces injustice, announces judgment and restoration, and foretells the ruler who would be born in Bethlehem. Its central theme is to act justly, love mercy, and walk humbly with God.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_nahum_synopsis">Nahum announces the fall of Nineveh and God's judgment on oppression and violence. Its central theme is that God is just in the face of evil.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_habakkuk_synopsis">Habakkuk questions God about injustice and evil and learns to trust, receiving the answer that “the righteous shall live by faith.” Its central theme is persevering faith in the face of unanswered questions.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_zephaniah_synopsis">Zephaniah warns of the day of the Lord and promises restoration and joy to a faithful remnant. Its central theme is the balance between judgment and hope.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_haggai_synopsis">Haggai urges those who returned from exile to rebuild the temple and to put God first. Its central theme is the reordering of priorities around God.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_zechariah_synopsis">Zechariah receives visions that encourage the rebuilding of the temple and point to the coming of the Messiah. Its central theme is hope, renewal, and the future restoration brought by God.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_malachi_synopsis">Malachi confronts the people's spiritual apathy and corrupted worship and announces the coming of the messenger who would prepare the way. Its central theme is sincere faithfulness and the return to God.</string>

    <!-- Gospels -->
    <string name="bible_book_matthew_synopsis">Matthew presents Jesus as the promised Messiah and king, gathering His teachings — such as the Sermon on the Mount — His miracles, death, and resurrection. Its central theme is Jesus as the fulfillment of the promises and the values of the Kingdom of heaven.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_mark_synopsis">Mark offers a fast-paced account of Jesus' ministry, emphasizing His actions, miracles, and the road to the cross. Its central theme is Jesus as servant and the cost of following Him.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_luke_synopsis">Luke carefully narrates the life of Jesus, from birth to ascension, with special attention to the outcast, to prayer, and to joy. Its central theme is the compassion of God that reaches all people.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_john_synopsis">John presents Jesus as the eternal Word and the Son of God through signs and the “I am” sayings. Its central theme is believing in Jesus in order to have eternal life.</string>

    <!-- History (New Testament) -->
    <string name="bible_book_acts_synopsis">Acts recounts how, after Jesus' ascension and the coming of the Holy Spirit at Pentecost, the apostles spread the gospel from Jerusalem to Rome, with a focus on Paul's missionary journeys. Its central theme is the growth of the church through the work of the Spirit.</string>

    <!-- Pauline Epistles -->
    <string name="bible_book_romans_synopsis">Romans presents the gospel in an orderly way — sin, justification by faith, life in the Spirit, and God's plan. Its central theme is salvation by grace through faith.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_1_corinthians_synopsis">1 Corinthians addresses the divisions, immorality, and many questions of the church in Corinth, including the famous chapter on love. Its central theme is unity, holiness, and love in community life.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_2_corinthians_synopsis">2 Corinthians contains Paul's defense of his ministry and his reflections on suffering, comfort, and generosity. Its central theme is strength made perfect in weakness and sincerity in service.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_galatians_synopsis">Galatians confronts a return to legalism and defends justification by faith and the freedom led by the Spirit. Its central theme is the freedom of the gospel.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_ephesians_synopsis">Ephesians describes the riches the believer has in Christ and the unity of the church, calling for a life worthy of that calling. Its central theme is the new identity and unity in Christ.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_philippians_synopsis">Philippians is a joyful letter written from prison, in which Paul thanks the Philippians and urges them to unity and humility, pointing to the example of Christ. Its central theme is joy and contentment in Christ.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_colossians_synopsis">Colossians exalts the supremacy of Christ over all things and warns against false teaching. Its central theme is the complete sufficiency of Christ.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_1_thessalonians_synopsis">1 Thessalonians encourages a young church in faith, love, and hope, with teaching about the return of Christ. Its central theme is living in the hope of the Lord's coming.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_2_thessalonians_synopsis">2 Thessalonians corrects confusion about the day of the Lord and urges perseverance in work. Its central theme is steadfastness and order while awaiting Christ.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_1_timothy_synopsis">1 Timothy provides Paul's guidance to Timothy on church leadership, sound doctrine, and godly living. Its central theme is order and integrity in the life of the church.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_2_timothy_synopsis">2 Timothy is Paul's final letter, in which he urges Timothy to remain faithful and to guard the gospel. Its central theme is perseverance and faithfulness to the end.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_titus_synopsis">Titus contains Paul's instructions for appointing leaders and teaching sound doctrine on the island of Crete. Its central theme is faith expressed in good works.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_philemon_synopsis">Philemon is a personal letter in which Paul appeals for Philemon to receive back his runaway slave Onesimus, now as a brother. Its central theme is forgiveness and reconciliation.</string>

    <!-- General Epistles -->
    <string name="bible_book_hebrews_synopsis">Hebrews presents Jesus as superior to all — the high priest and the fulfillment of the old covenant — and calls for perseverance in faith. Its central theme is the supremacy of Christ and faith that endures.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_james_synopsis">James offers practical wisdom on living out faith through actions, words, and care for others. Its central theme is that faith without works is dead.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_1_peter_synopsis">1 Peter encourages suffering Christians to stand firm in hope and holiness. Its central theme is hope and holiness amid trials.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_2_peter_synopsis">2 Peter warns against false teachers and urges growth in godliness and watchfulness for the return of Christ. Its central theme is truth and maturity in the face of deception.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_1_john_synopsis">1 John assures believers of the certainty of eternal life and calls them to love and to walk in the light. Its central theme is the assurance of faith through love and truth.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_2_john_synopsis">2 John is a brief letter urging believers to walk in truth and love and to guard against deceivers. Its central theme is truth and love walking together.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_3_john_synopsis">3 John is a personal letter commending hospitality and faithfulness, contrasting good and bad leaders. Its central theme is supporting what is good and true.</string>
    <string name="bible_book_jude_synopsis">Jude warns against false teachers and urges believers to contend for the faith. Its central theme is perseverance and discernment.</string>

    <!-- Apocalypse -->
    <string name="bible_book_revelation_synopsis">Revelation, through symbolic visions given to John, portrays the conflict between good and evil, the final judgment, and the renewal of all things in a new heaven and a new earth. Its central theme is hope and the ultimate victory of Christ.</string>

    <string name="synopsis">Synopsis</string>
    <string name="chapters">Chapters</string>
    <string name="reading_progress">Reading Progress</string>
    <string name="read_count">%1$d / %2$d read</string>
    <string name="tap_to_mark">tap to mark</string>
    <string name="show_more">Show more</string>
    <string name="show_less">Show less</string>
    <string name="mark_all_as_read">Mark all as read</string>
    <string name="mark_all_as_unread">Mark all as unread</string>
    <string name="read_count_suffix"> read</string>

</resources>
